Finding Aid for Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor records, 1866-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor records 1866-2011
Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.
85612 Bz 2
Minutes, financial records, book lists, and clippings; also scrapbook, 1953-1968, concerning the Ann Arbor Public Library; commemorative tenth anniversary volume, 1876, containing message to the women of 1976.
3.1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated from multiple sources. One portion of the records was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 ). Another was received from the Ladies Library Association (donor no. 5863 ) in periodic accessions.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor was established in 1866 as a subscription library with dues set a three dollars a year. The idea of a free public library was discussed early on with the thought that the city might match support for the library. In 1870, the organization proposed that the city council take over the subscription library and make it a public one. This idea was rejected. In 1879, the Association rejected the idea of combining its collection with that of the Board of Education. Instead, it purchased land on East Huron and in 1885 moved into its new quarters.
In the first decade of the twentieth century, the Association began negotiations with Andrew Carnegie for a grant to build a new building. Also needing municipal support, the Association turned to the Ann Arbor School Board, and together they tentatively agreed to provide the necessary support (along with a $15,000 Carnegie grant) for a public library building. Negotiations stalled over the site of the new library. Instead, and following close upon the burning down in 1904 of the old high school, it was agreed that the library would form a wing of the new high school. In 1907, with the completion of the new high school and library, the Board of Education invited the Ladies Library Association to join the school district library. In 1916, the Association presented their collection of books to the library and deeded their Huron Street property to the Ann Arbor Public Schools.
The records of the Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor include minutes of meetings, anniversary and celebratory materials, clippings and photographs, and financial records. The records of the Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor are arranged in two series: Organizational Records and Audio Cassettes.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Public Library.; Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Organizational Records
  The Organizational Records include minutes of meetings, reports, book wish lists, anniversary and celebratory materials, clippings and photographs, and financial records. There are also materials relating to the history of the Ladies Library Association and its members. Organizational records for the years following 1970 are also organized in chronological files.
  - Record books
    (microfilm copy available)
    - No. 1 1866-1872 (Box 1)
    - No. 3 1879-1890 (Box 1)
    - No. 4 1890-1901 (Box 1)
    - No. 5 1901-1908 (Box 1)
    - No. 6 1908-1953 (Box 1)
  - Financial records 1881-1962, 7 volumes (Box 1)
  - Book lists circa 1916-1948, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Notebook containing photocopies of records in collection (Box 1)
  - Chronological files 1970-2009, 22 folders (Box 1)
  - Secretary's books 1930-1995, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Secretary's records 1930-1985, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Committee meetings 1995-2011, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Book Committee 2001-2010 (Box 3)
  - Commemorative volume 1976 (Box 3)
    (closed until 2076)
  - 1891 report (25th anniversary) (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor District Library (Box 3)
  - Autobiographies of Members 1976 (Box 3)
  - Bookplates (Box 3)
  - Centennial Celebration of the Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor 1966 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Commemorative tenth anniversary volume 1876 containing message to the women of 1976, original and photocopy (Box 3)
  - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 3)
  - Financial Records (Box 3)
  - History (Box 3)
  - Membership Lists (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1953-1968 (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea; include by-laws, reports, resolutions, etc., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
- Audio Cassettes of meetings
  The Audio Cassettes contain recordings of meetings of the Ladies Library Association.
  - October 31, 1986, 3 tapes (Box 4)
  - April 28, 1987 (Box 4)
  - 1988 (Box 4)
  - April 26, 1991, 2 tapes (Box 4)
  - April 19, 1996 (Box 4)
  - October 25, 1996 (Box 4)
  - April 25, 1997 (Box 4)
  - October 17, 1997 (Box 4)
  - May 8, 1998 (Box 4)
  - October 30, 1998 (Box 4)
  - April, 1999 (Box 4)
  - October 10, 1999 (Box 4)
  - April, 2000 (Box 4)
  - November, 2000, 2 tapes (Box 4)
  - April 2001 (Box 4)
  - Unlabeled, 2 tapes (Box 4)